Harold Bauer Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Harold Bauer Collection1880-1951 (bulk 1920-1951)
ML31.B43
Bauer, Harold, 1873-1951
1250 items 18 boxes 10 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The material in the Harold Bauer collection consists of correspondence with musicians such as Ernest Bloch, Nadia Boulanger, Pablo Casals, Gabriel Fauré, Percy Grainger, Jascha Heifetz, Josef Hofmann, Gustav Holst, Vincent d'Indy, Fritz Kreisler, Charles Martin Loeffler, Pierre Monteux, Moritz Moszkowski, Vladimir de Pachmann, Ignace Jan Paderewski, Isidore Philipp, Henry Prunières, Carl Ruggles, Carlos Salzedo, Gustave Schirmer, Leopold Stokowski, and Efrem Zimbalist; music which includes several holograph transcriptions and editions prepared by Bauer and others; artwork and photographs, among the latter, inscribed photographs of Ernest Bloch, Claude Debussy, Ignace Jan Paderewski, Leopold Stokowski, and Rabindranath Tagore; writings by and about Bauer, containing articles and speeches by Bauer on a wide range of music-related topics; publicity material regarding Bauer and other performers, including concert programs and information about concert tours; press, journal, and magazine clippings, the majority of which are about Bauer's performances; awards; and realia.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Bauer, Harold, 1873-1951--Archives.; Bauer, Harold, 1873-1951--Correspondence.; Bauer, Harold, 1873-1951--Manuscripts.; Bauer, Harold, 1873-1951--Photographs.; Bauer, Harold, 1873-1951.; Bauer, Harold, 1873-1951.; Bauer, Harold, 1873-1951. Harold Bauer, his book.; Bloch, Ernest, 1880-1959--Correspondence.; Boulanger, Nadia--Correspondence.; Casals, Pablo, 1876-1973--Correspondence.; Fauré, Gabriel, 1845-1924--Correspondence.; Grainger, Percy, 1882-1961--Correspondence.; Heifetz, Jascha, 1901-1987--Correspondence.; Hofmann, Josef, 1876-1957--Correspondence.; Holst, Gustav, 1874-1934--Correspondence.; Indy, Vincent d', 1851-1931--Correspondence.; Kreisler, Fritz, 1875-1962--Correspondence.; Loeffler, Charles Martin, 1861-1935--Correspondence.; Monteux, Pierre, 1875-1964--Correspondence.; Moszkowski, Moritz, 1854-1925--Correspondence.; Pachmann, Vladimir de, 1848-1933--Correspondence.; Paderewski, Ignace Jan, 1860-1941--Correspondence.; Philipp, Isidore, 1863-1958--Correspondence.; Prunières, Henry, 1886-1942--Correspondence.; Ruggles, Carl, 1876-1971--Correspondence.; Salzedo, Carlos, 1885-1961--Correspondence.; Schirmer, Gustave, 1890-1965--Correspondence.; Stokowski, Leopold, 1882-1977--Correspondence.; Zimbalist, Efrem--Correspondence.
Organizations
Beethoven Association (New York, N.Y.)
Subjects
Music--20th century--History and criticism.; Music--20th century.; Music--Manuscripts.; Musicians--Photographs.; Pianists--United States.
Form/Genre
Artifacts (Object genre); Awards.; Clippings (Information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographic prints.; Programs (Documents); Promotional materials.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Harold Bauer; 1928-1929
Gift; Harold Bauer; 1934-1935
Gift; Wynne Pyle Bauer; 1951
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Access and Restrictions
The Harold Bauer Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
While infrequently considered by modern musical scholarship, Harold Bauer (1873-1951) held an eminent position in the musical life of his time. Throughout his career he was regarded as one of the greatest living pianists, a successor to the tradition of Liszt, Paderewski and Brahms, and a celebrated interpreter of the music of Schumann, Brahms and Franck. He was one of the first to champion the music of Debussy and of Ravel, who dedicated the "Ondine" movement of his Gaspard de la nuit to the pianist. Bauer also had considerable fame as a recitalist, performing with such accomplished performers as Pablo Casals, Fritz Kreisler, Jacques Thibaud, Ossip Gabrilowitsch, and the Flonzaley String Quartet.
As a performer, Bauer continually sought to attain and to define the highest musical standards, and to convey them to the widest possible audience. To this end, Bauer founded the Beethoven Association in 1918, which, through its sponsorship of public concerts featuring the finest musicians of the time, and through its financial support of musicians and institutions alike, greatly contributed to the development of American musical culture in the first half of this century. As an educator, Bauer edited many editions of piano music (most notably of Bach, Brahms, and the complete piano works of Schumann), several of which are still in print today. In his later years, he taught at the Manhattan School of Music and at the University of Miami, and gave frequent lectures and master classes throughout the country. Bauer was also keenly interested in a wide range of musical topics and has left a substantial amount of writings on various composers and their works, interpretation, performance practice, and piano technique.
Bauer's interest in education, however, was not limited to musicians; he recognized that musical culture must extend to as large an audience as possible in order to be fully realized. For this audience, Bauer wrote many articles which treated more general musical topics; his autobiography and these articles all bear the stamp of his particular erudition and wit. For these reasons he was held in high esteem by both his contemporaries among professional musicians and by a larger public, for whom his art possessed an almost "popular" fame.
Date Event
1873, Apr. 28 Born, Kingston-on-Thames, near London
circa 1878-1882 Received first musical education at home; aunt gave him first violin lessons, and father provided him with piano instruction some years later
1882 First public appearance as a violin soloist, Saint James' Hall, London
1893 Left England for Paris, where he resided for the next twenty years Began coaching with Ignace Paderewski, which influenced his decision to pursue a career as a concert pianist
1894 Debut in Paris. Accepted offer of a concert tour through Russia as accompanist (on piano as well as on violin) for the singer Louise Nikita (pseudonym of Louise Nicholson), which lasted until the spring of the following year
circa 1896 Frequented Parisian musical circles and became acquainted with several notable figures, including Debussy, Ravel, Saint-Saëns, Enesco, Casals and Kreisler; with the two latter performers, Bauer began a lengthy period of touring
1900 American debut in Boston as piano soloist in Brahms' Concerto no. 1 in D minor with the Boston Symphony Orchestra, conducted by Wilhelm Gericke (the work's Boston première)
1918 Founded the Beethoven Association in New York; its first concert was presented on Nov. 4 of the following year
circa 1920-1948 Devoted himself to the pursuit of interests which were of highest importance to him: concertizing, writing (on music education and music criticism), and preparing editions of piano music for the publishing firm of G. Schirmer
1924, July 10 Became American citizen
1948 Published autobiography Harold Bauer, His Book. New York: W.W. Norton
1951, Mar. 12 Died, Miami, Florida
Scope and Content Note
The material in the Harold Bauer Collection is divided into ten sections. From a musicological perspective, the material of most notable interest is found in the Correspondence series, which includes Bauer's correspondence with many of this century's most important musical figures, such as Ernest Bloch, Nadia Boulanger, Pablo Casals, Gabriel Fauré, Percy Grainger, Jascha Heifetz, Josef Hofmann, Gustav Holst, Vincent d'Indy, Fritz Kreisler, Charles Martin Loeffler, Pierre Monteux, Moritz Moszkowski, Vladimir de Pachmann, Ignace Jan Paderewski, Isidore Philipp, Henry Prunières, Carl Ruggles, Carlos Salzedo, Gustave Schirmer, Leopold Stokowski, and Efrem Zimbalist; the Music series, which contains several holograph transcriptions and editions prepared by Bauer and others; the Iconography series, which includes both artwork and photographs, and among the latter, inscribed photographs of Ernest Bloch, Claude Debussy, Ignace Jan Paderewski, Leopold Stokowski, and Rabindranath Tagore; and the Writings by and about Harold Bauer series, which contains articles and speeches by Bauer on a wide range of music-related topics. The collection also includes publicity material regarding Bauer and other performers, including concert programs and information about concert tours; press clippings, the majority of which are about Bauer, his performances, or about others; clippings from journals and magazines about or by Bauer; awards; and realia. The variety of material contained within this collection reflects the multi-faceted personality and diverse interests of a man devoted to the pursuit of his art, and its appreciation by its listeners.
A copy of the finding aid is located in BOX/FOLDER 1/1.
Kevin LaVine, June 1995
*Two additional medals awarded to HB (one medal, presented by the Philharmonic Society of London, 1912; and one silver medal) and included in the collection are presently housed in the Musical Instrument Vault's Map Case. Photographs of all medals awarded to HB can be found in Box 12, Folder 50; one photograph of the plaster castings of HB's hands, contained in Box 13 of the collection, can be found in Box 12, Folder 48.
The following issues were discarded through the Library of Congress Exchange and Gift Division: The Musical Quarterly (published at New York: G. Schirmer, Inc.), May 1995: October 1926 (v. XII, no. 4, part II); July 1927 (v. XIII, no. 3); January 1932 (v. XVIII, no. 1); October 1932 (v. XVIII, no. 4, part II).
Organization of the Harold Bauer Collection
The Harold Bauer Collection is organized in ten series:
Music
Correspondence
Writings by and about Harold Bauer
Writings, Other
Clippings
Publicity
Awards & Certificates
Miscellany
Iconography
Realia
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010563505
Container List
- Music (Box 1-2)
  The Music series is represented by holograph materials by Harold Bauer, printed and photo reproductions.
  Arranged alphabetically by composer and title therein.
  - Bach, Johann Sebastian
    - Come unto me. [Sonata, A minor, vn solo: Aria.], HB holograph score, 2 p.; Arr. HB for voice and piano (English). (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Toccata [C minor, organ solo]., HB holograph score, 19 p.; Arr. HB for pf solo. (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Bauer, Harold
    - The B.A. bids you welcome (Greeting). Mixed choir (SATB) (English)., Holograph score, 1 p.; Includes additional annotated holograph score of same, 1 p.; with additional "greeting" material (vocal line only) for Olga Samaroff, Walter Damrosch, and Rubin Goldmark; holograph, 2 p.;; Also includes vn obbligato part, holograph, in one half page. (Box-folder 1/4)
    - [Cadenzas for Mozart's Piano Concerto in A major.], Holograph scores, 2, 3 p.; Pf solo. (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Invention for modulation in two voices., Holograph score, 2 p.; Pf solo. (Box-folder 1/6)
    - The pianist's warming up exercises., Photoreproduced copy of holograph score, 2 p.; Pf solo. (Box-folder 1/7)
    - A simple primer for practical keyboard modulation., Photoreproduced copy of holograph score, 2 p.; Pf solo. (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Ye sweet retreat (after William Boyce). New York: G. Schirmer, 1943., Two pianos. (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Ye sweet retreat (after William Boyce)., Holograph scores for 2 pianos; 2, 2 p. (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Beethoven, Ludwig van
    - [Sonata, no. 23, op. 57, "Appassionata" (?)]., Photographed copy of unidentified manuscript.; Pf solo.; (holograph?) sketches, 8 p. (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Boyce, William
    - A new song for Solomon., Photoreproduced copy of unidentifiable printed score, 2 p.; Fl, voice, pf (figured bass) (English). (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Brahms, Johannes
    - My faithful heart rejoices. [Herzlich tut mich erfreuen, op. 122, no. 4.], HB holograph score with pasteovers, 3 p.; Arr. HB for pf solo. (Box-folder 1/12)
  - von Bülow, Hans
    - If order is Heaven's first law., Photoreproduced copy of Berliner Musikalien-Druckerei edition, n.d., 4 p.; Voice and pf (English). (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Deis, Carl
    - Fleet fingers (Toccatina)., Photoreproduced copy, 4 p., bound.; Pf solo.; Date: Copyright 1950 by G. Schirmer, Inc. (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Franck, César
    - Variationen über Von diesen Händchen, so sanft, so meich. Leipzig: Fr. Hofmeister, n.d., Pf solo.; pl. no. 1337 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - Grainger, Percy
    - British Folk Music Settings: 6. Irish Tune from County Derry. London: Schott & Co., 1911., Pf solo.; Inscribed by the composer. (Box-folder 1/16)
  - Jones, Robert
    - Ye love of change., HB holo- graph score, 2 p.; Arr. by HB for voice, pf (English). (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus
    - Sonata [D major, pf solo]., HB holograph scores, 27, 14 p.; Arr. by HB for pf four hands. (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Purcell, Henry
    - Siciliano., HB holograph score, 5 p.; Arr. by HB for pf solo. (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Royce, Edward
    - Noon tide Boston: Arthur P. Schmidt Co., 1921., Pf solo (Box-folder 2/1)
    - A set of eight: VI. "... darkly"; IV. Interlude; V. Joyance New York: G. Schirmer, 1919., Pf solos; Also includes holograph (?) scores for: II. Aubade (2 p.); VIII. Chorale (5 p. with pasteover); VI. Danse (3 p.); VII. "... Darkly" (2 p.); V. Interlude (2 p.); I. Invocation (2 p.); IV. Joyance (3 p. with pasteover); III. Spirit of Night (2 p.). [Titles and order of pieces within this set vary from the order given in the printed score.] (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Theme and Variations, A minor New York: G. Schirmer, 1917., Pf solo; Includes manuscript material. (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Variations in A minor, Holograph (?) score, 13 p.; Pf solo (Box-folder 2/4)
  - Schumann, Robert
    - Sonata, A minor, op. 105, Holograph arranger's piano score (1944), 33 p.; Arr. HB; Piano and violin (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Sonata, D minor, op. 121, HB holograph scores for pf (32 p.), vn part (26 p.).; Vn, pf; Edited by HB (Box-folder 2/6)
    - [Studien für den Pedal-Flügel, op. 56, no. 4.], HB holograph scores, 5, 5 p.; Arr. HB for two pf (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Sunrise [Gesänge der Frühe, op. 133, no. 3]., HB holograph scores, 6, 5 p.; Arr. HB for two pf (Box-folder 2/8)
  - Sonneck, Oscar G.
    - Ein Kleiner Lieder Cyklus zu Gedichten von Theodor Storm, op. 18 (1918)., Photoreproduction of holograph score, 12 p.; Voice, pf (German).; Inscribed by the composer on front cover. (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Vier Pessimistische Lieder, op. 17 (1917)., Photoreproduction of holograph score, 13 p.; For voice, pf (German).; Inscribed by the composer on front cover. (Box-folder 2/10)
  - [Unidentified]
    - Fandango, Photographed copy, 4 p.; Pf solo (Box-folder 2/11)
    - Flourish (French Soldiers' War Tune), HB holograph score, 10 p.; Arr. HB for two pf (Box-folder 2/12)
  - [Unidentified reverse print, 1 p.] (Box-folder 2/13)
- Correspondence (Box 3)
  The Correspondence series is represented by many letters from Harold Bauer's peers (number of items in each folder appear within parentheses following the folder name).
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Aeolian Company (4) (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Aldrich, Richard (2) (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Ashe, Mrs. Bowman Foster (2) (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Baldwin Piano Company (8) (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Barrère, Georges (1) (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Bauer, Harold, 1911-1951, undated, Folders: Bauer, Harold, 1911-29 (5) BOX: 3/6 Bauer, Harold, 1930-51 (11) BOX: 3/7 Bauer, Harold, undated (3) BOX: 3/8 Bauer, Harold: "Lessons by mail" to Wynne Pyle (later Mrs. HB) (12) BOX: 3/9 (Box-folder 3/6-8)
  - Bitter, John (10) (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Bloch, Ernest (7) (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Boulanger, Nadia (3) (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Casals, Pablo (1) (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Coolidge, Elizabeth Sprague (1) (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Damrosch, Frank (5) and Walter Damrosch (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Deis, Carl (2) (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Delius, Frederick (photoreproduction of ALS, 2 p., to P. Grainger) (1) (Box-folder 3/17)
  - Einstein, Alfred (1) (Box-folder 3/18)
  - Enesco, Georges (1) (Box-folder 3/19)
  - Engel, Carl (3) (Box-folder 3/20)
  - Erskine, John (1) (Box-folder 3/21)
  - Fauré, Gabriel (1) (Box-folder 3/22)
  - Gabrilowitsch, Ossip (4) and Clara Gabrilowitsch (Box-folder 3/23)
  - Ganz, Rudolph (1) (Box-folder 3/24)
  - Gavin, Basil (4) (Box-folder 3/25)
  - Goodrich, Wallace (4) (Box-folder 3/26)
  - Grainger, Percy (22) and Elsa Grainger (Box-folder 3/27)
  - Hale, Philip (1) (Box-folder 3/28)
  - Heifetz, Jascha (1) (Box-folder 3/29)
  - Hess, Myra (1) (Box-folder 3/30)
  - Hofmann, Josef (2) (Box-folder 3/31)
  - Holst, Gustav (1) (Box-folder 3/32)
  - Honeywell, Eugenia (2) (Box-folder 3/33)
  - Huberman, Bronislaw (1) (Box-folder 3/34)
  - d'Indy, Vincent (1) (Box-folder 3/35)
  - van Katwijk, Paul (6) (Box-folder 3/36)
  - Kortshak, Alice (1) (Box-folder 3/37)
  - Kreisler, Fritz (4) (Box-folder 3/38)
  - Library of Congress (4) (Box-folder 3/39)
  - Loeffler, Charles Martin (4) (Box-folder 3/40)
  - Manhattan School of Music (NY) (12) (Box-folder 3/41)
  - Martin, Mary (1) (Box-folder 3/42)
  - Mason, Henry Lowell (11) (Box-folder 3/43)
  - Mason & Hamlin Company (6) (Box-folder 3/44)
  - Miami, University of (Coral Gables, FL) (9) (Box-folder 3/45)
  - Monteux, Pierre (4) (Box-folder 3/46)
  - Moor, Emmanuel (8) (Box-folder 3/47)
  - Moszkowski, Moritz (1) (Box-folder 3/48)
  - W. W. Norton & Company (11) (Box-folder 3/49)
  - de Pachmann, Vladimir (2) (Box-folder 3/50)
  - Paderewski, Ignace Jan (1) (Box-folder 3/51)
  - Peabody Conservatory of Music (Baltimore, MD) (2) (Box-folder 3/52)
  - Philipp, Isidore (6) (Box-folder 3/53)
  - Picquart, Georges (3) (Box-folder 3/54)
  - Prunières, Henry (1) (Box-folder 3/55)
  - Putnam, Brenda (4) (Box-folder 3/56)
  - Rabaud, Henri (1) (Box-folder 3/57)
  - Radio Corporation of America/RCA Victor (1) (Box-folder 3/58)
  - Reese, Gustave (4) (Box-folder 3/59)
  - Rosenthal, Marie (1) (Box-folder 3/60)
  - Ruggles, Carl (3) (Box-folder 3/61)
  - Rummel, Walter Morse (4) (Box-folder 3/62)
  - Salmon, Joseph (2) (Box-folder 3/63)
  - Salzedo, Carlos (1) (Box-folder 3/64)
  - Schenck, Martin (4) (Box-folder 3/65)
  - Schirmer, Gustave (4) (Box-folder 3/66)
  - Schumann Memorial Foundation (5) (Box-folder 3/67)
  - Sembrich, Marcella (1) (Box-folder 3/68)
  - Steinway, Theodore (1) (Box-folder 3/69)
  - Stokowski, Leopold (3) and Olga Samaroff Stokowski (Box-folder 3/70)
  - Thibaud, Jacques (1) (Box-folder 3/71)
  - Trinity University (San Antonio, TX) (9) (Box-folder 3/72)
  - Van Loon, Henrik, 1931-1944, undated, Folders: Van Loon, Henrik, 1931-36 (10) BOX: 3/73 Van Loon, Henrik, 1937-44; undated (12) BOX: 3/74 (Box-folder 3/73-74)
  - Wilcox & White Piano Roll Company (4) (Box-folder 3/75)
  - Yale University, School of Music (2) (Box-folder 3/76)
  - Zimbalist, Efrem (1) (Box-folder 3/77)
  - Miscellaneous, A-C (30) (Box-folder 3/78)
  - Miscellaneous, D-H (21) (Box-folder 3/79)
  - Miscellaneous, I-P (33) (Box-folder 3/80)
  - Miscellaneous, R-Z (40) (Box-folder 3/81)
  - Unidentified (6) (Box-folder 3/82)
- Writings by and about Harold Bauer (Box 4-5)
  The Writings by and about series consists of three subseries: Harold Bauer, His Book (autobiography); Speeches by Harold Bauer; Speeches about Harold Bauer. The first subseries, Harold Bauer, His Book (autobiography), consists of holograph manuscript, previously bound in several spiral notebooks.
  Arranged by subject, title or provenance.
  - Harold Bauer, His Book (autobiography) (Box 4)
    - "London/1873 to 1892"; 91, 17 p., in ink and in pencil, with pasteovers. (Box-folder 4/1)
    - "Paris/1893-1913"; 65 p., in ink, with pasteovers and inserted printed material. (Box-folder 4/2)
    - "Paris/1900-1913 (continued)"; 85 p., in ink, with pasteovers. (Box-folder 4/3)
    - "Chapter"; 48 p., in ink, with pasteovers. (Box-folder 4/4)
    - "Chapter"; 33 p., in ink, with pasteovers. (Box-folder 4/5)
    - "Chapter"; 35 p., in ink, with pasteovers. (Box-folder 4/6)
    - "Chapter"; 31 p., in ink, with pasteovers. (Box-folder 4/7)
    - "Chapter"; 22 p., in ink, with pasteovers. (Box-folder 4/8)
    - "Chapter"; 20 p., in ink. (Box-folder 4/9)
    - "Chapter"; 27 p., in ink. (Box-folder 4/10)
    - "Chapter"; 22 p., in ink. (Box-folder 4/11)
    - "Chapter"; 19 p., in ink, with pasteovers. (Box-folder 4/12)
    - "Havana, a green cigar, a hat and a bottle of rum"; 35 p., in ink, with pasteovers. (Box-folder 4/13)
    - Typescript, p. 50-81, complete. (Box-folder 4/14)
    - Typescript, 11 p. (miscellaneous pages between p. 22 and p. 135). (Box-folder 4/15)
    - Typescript, 88 p., unnumbered ("p. 187 ?" on first page). (Box-folder 4/16)
    - Typescript, 17, 5 (printed), 3 p., unnumbered ("p. 298 ?" on first page). (Box-folder 4/17)
    - Typescript, 14 p., unnumbered, with 5 p. pasteovers in HB's hand. (Box-folder 4/18)
  - Speeches & Articles by Harold Bauer (Box 5)
    - "Address by HB at Cleveland, Ohio, December 11th, 1930," typed, 11 p. (2 copies). (Box-folder 5/1)
    - [Address to the Beethoven Association]: "From Rabelais-/Chapter: Abbey de Thélème," holograph, undated, in ink, 1 p. (Box-folder 5/2)
    - "Address to the Neighborhood Music School," (New York, 1928 Apr 8), printed pamphlet, 8 p. (2 copies). (Box-folder 5/3)
    - [Address to Omaha music teachers], typed, undated, 4 p. (missing first page?). (Box-folder 5/4)
    - "All Join In," clipping from Music Clubs Magazine, c. 1933, 2 p. (Box-folder 5/5)
    - [Amateur musicians and music clubs], typed, undated, 1 p.; carbon copy of typed copy, undated, 1 p. (Box-folder 5/6)
    - "Answer to Correspondents" (regarding Chopin's Polonaise, Franck's Variations), holograph, undated, ink, 1 p. (Box-folder 5/7)
    - "Beethoven/Lecture...for Beethoven Association," holograph, ink and pencil, undated, 18 p. (Box-folder 5/8)
    - "Beethoven Association/April 18th, 1925./Address of the President at/the General Meeting," typed, with pasteovers, 11 p. (Box-folder 5/9)
    - "B.A. [Beethoven Association] Feb 12, 1934," holograph, 2 p. (Box-folder 5/10)
    - [Definition of music], holograph, undated, ink, 1 p. (Box-folder 5/11)
    - "Delusions of Piano Technic/Even Scale as a Handicap - Emotional and Mechanical Studies Inseparable," clipping from New York (?), December 1928, 2 p. (Box-folder 5/12)
    - "Dinner with [Vladimir] de Pachmann - New York, June 17, 1924 or [2]5 ?", holograph, ink and pencil, 6 p. (Box-folder 5/13)
    - "The Evolution of Musical Instruments/and/the Development of the Symphony Orchestra from the 16th to the 20th Centuries," holograph, undated, ink and pencil, 34 p. (Box-folder 5/14)
    - "Expression in Music," holograph, undated, ink, 9 p. (Box-folder 5/15)
    - [Foreword to a piano method book], holograph, undated, ink and pencil, 5 p. (Box-folder 5/16)
    - "The Growth of Music in America," (Address to the Music Division of the National Federation of Settlements, Washington DC, 1923 May 16). Printed in The Musical Courier, 1923 Jun 7 (Box-folder 5/17)
    - [Inborn musical sense and amateur musicians], typed, undated, 4 p. (incomplete); carbon copy of original, undated, 6 p. (complete). (Box-folder 5/18)
    - HB and Wollstein, R.H. "Let the Amateur Make Music," clipping from The Etude, July 1931, 1 p. (Box-folder 5/19)